A Guide to the Richard Harding Davis Letters Concerning South Africa and the Boer War
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- [1900] April 4 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to [Rebecca Harding Davis?], East London, South Africa, on R.M.S. Moor stationery, sent a request to Secretary of State John M. Hay to get them into Pretoria, who said he would be glad to see them there; they arrive at Durban tomorrow where they will stay a day and two nights, and then go on board the Konig for Delagoa Bay [off the coast of Mozambique]; while in Pretoria, Davis hopes "to write a book from both sides giving my ideas of the English in the field and the Boer at home. With the exception of Churchill who 'had to' I shall be the only correspondent who has been permitted to go on both sides.", 10 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:29)
- [1900] April 5 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Royal Hotel, Durban, Natal, stationery, enjoyed a rickshaw ride with Cecil and took a photograph of her and her "attendants"; Commandant objected to their going to Pretoria and was inclined to refuse them passes to leave Durban for Delagoa Bay but after Davis wired many of his friends in South Africa they were eventually vouched for by the High Commissioner; and Davis includes details of their shopping in Durban; 5 pages on 2 leaves, and black and white photograph of Cecil Davis in rickshaw (Box-folder 1:30)
- [1900 April 22?] "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], Grand Hotel, Pretoria, S.A.R., stationery, writes that he and Cecil are settling down in Pretoria and are going to keep house in the home of a refugee, moving in today; the Chicago contingent [Irish-Americans who came out as an ambulance corps] are going down to President Kruger's to bid him farewell; Richard hopes to have some fine stories soon, see the President, and get a cart to drive down to [Kroonstad?] and see the Boer army in the field, 2 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:31)
- [1900] April 23 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Pretoria Club stationery, Pretoria, describes the house, that belonged to an English refugee, given to him and Cecil to use for two pounds a month, which includes two horses, a carriage and driver; describes Cecil's cooking experiences; and the purchase by the Irish brigade of a plain gold bracelet for Cecil with the engraving "From the Irish American Ambulance Corps to Mrs. R.H. Davis" and the motto of Chicago "I will,", 4 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:32)
- [1900] April 25 Cecil [Clark Davis] to Nora [Davis], Pretoria, writes about their settling in as householders, lacking only a cook to be complete; their current plans are to stay in Pretoria until June 5 th and then sail in easy stages to Zanzibar, Mozambique, etc. to Naples and then go by rail until they reach Aix, reaching America in August; they both plan to go to the front in a day or two; they see much of [General "Koos"] De la Rey and Coolidge; and Richard is busy reporting on all the interesting things that are happening, 3 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:33)
- [1900] May 4 [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Families," plans on going to the front with Cecil tonight, had planned on accompanying the Boer artillery to Brandfort, but it was just taken by the British, 2 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:34)
- [1900] May 8 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to [Davis and Clark families ?], Grand Hotel, Ventersberg, describes their adventures in the Free State from the time they left Pretoria on May 4 th to attempt to go to Brandsfort, then Winburg, and finally Smaaldel, all of which were taken by the British before they could reach the area; yesterday they rode out with [Otto von Lossberg] and camped at a Boer farm, just behind the Boer trenches on the Sand River, with the British six miles away; Cecil created a sensation among the Boers since all the women had fled; they met President [Marthinus] Steyn, who gave Cecil a flower from his coat and talked with her for some time; they decided to spend the night at [Jones's Hotel], Ventersberg and Cecil woke him to say the British were at the railway station, two hour's ride away but they have not arrived yet; and they are now free to travel wherever they want through the loan of [Otto von Lossberg]'s cart with two seats and five mules, 2 pages on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:35)
- [1900] May 18 Richard [Harding Davis] to "Dear Dad [Lemuel Clark Davis] and others of the Clark and Davis families," Pretoria, work on his Ledger and Scribner stories has prevented his writing a long letter before now; begins an account of Cecil and his adventures with the Boers from May 4 th until the present; writes about Captain [Otto von Lossberg], "a German baron who married in New Orleans and became an American citizen and who is now in command of Lossberg's Artillery in the Free State"; describes in greater detail their meeting with President Steyn and the letter he gave them to Dr. Reid, who ran an ambulance base on [Piet] Cronje's farm, instructing him to give Cecil something to sleep on; they returned to Ventersberg that night only to overhear an alarm about the closeness of the British given to the landlady, "a grand low comedy character from Brooklyn … sitting up in bed in curl papers, and with a Webley revolver"; having decided to go back to sleep, they were able to use Lossberg's cape cart and five mules to pack their things and head to the Sand River, spending the night at Cronje's farm where Dr. Reid gave Cecil his field mattress; they then used Lossberg's cart to pursue their next objective - to reach the railroad bridge over the Sand River; they found themselves between the Boer and British lines and stopped for lunch; about three o'clock they were captured by three Boers, "I was riding behind the cart and threw up my hands 'that quick,' but Cecil could not hear me yelling at her to stop on account of the noise of the cart - I knew if I rode after her they would shoot at me, and that if she did not stop, as they were shouting at her to do, they would shoot her. Under these trying circumstances I sat still - It caused quite a coolness on Cecil's part."; they were finally released by the three Boers and next met General Christiaan De Wet (1854–1922), who directed them to a farmhouse about five miles off where they could safely see the fighting the next day, although they decided to camp out on the veldt near a stream; they were awakened by the sound of bombardment and hurriedly tried to get out of the danger area, Cecil showing much self-possession and calm and even urging the Boers to make a stand; when the British were within five hundred yards of the Boer artillery and [Louis?] Botha's men made a break for it, Richard finally convinced Cecil to get on her pony and race for Ventersberg; when they arrived there, they found everyone harnessing up [their carts and wagons] and abandoning everything; Cecil determined to loot the cook from Jones Hotel to work for them in Pretoria; while helping her pack her things and anything else useful, the message came that the British were only fifteen minutes away, so Richard loaded the cook, Cecil, supplies, a dog and a kitten, in the cart, mounted his horse and left hurriedly for Kroonstad racing for thirty miles in five hours without one stop; at Kroonstad, President Steyn ordered a special car for Richard and Cecil and sent them off at once; they plan to return as soon as Davis reaches the Vaal where there must be a stand; the cook proves to be a treasure and Cecil is busy doing portraits in oil, 11 pages on 6 leaves (Box-folder 1:36)
- [1900] June 8 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on board the S.S. Kanzler, having decided to leave Pretoria when the British neared the capital, to avoid living under British martial law subject to the censor and not having anything they could do; writes about the Boers, "I know no class of men I admire as much or who today preserve the best and oldest ideas of charity, fairness, and goodwill to men"; The Sun correspondent, Allen Sangree joined them at Delagoa and was robbed of his notes on the Irish Brigade and other papers the night he arrived, apparently by British agents willing to return them for a consideration; describes how he and Sangree tried to get his papers back from the British consul in the port [of Lourenço Marques?]; many wives and children of the men of Pretoria and Johannesburg also on board the ship, 6 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:37)
- [1900] June 12 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on board the S.S. Kanzler, admits to a sincere longing to see family and home; describes the people and land of [Beira], Mozambique where he also mentions the presence of slaves; has run out of film and cannot get any more; Cecil is drawing and Richard writing for Scribners, 4 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:38)
- [1900] June 21 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], have made their last stop at Tanga, north of Zanzibar and just south of Mombasa, where they have seen jungle; Cecil was carried about on a sedan chair by four Somali boys; declares that this area is what people think of as the real Africa; and shared a story of a lion attack on a man in a [stopped?] railway car, 2 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:39)
- [1900] June 25 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to Nora [Davis], off the coast of Suakin, [Sudan], currently in the Red Sea and will arrive at Suez tomorrow; ship is very crowded with women and children and it is very hot; describes the practices of the second class passengers; and Richard shares his favorable impression of Zanzibar and mentions slavery again; 3 pages on 2 leaves, with a picture of their ship Konig (Box-folder 1:40)
- [1900] June 29 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], off the coast of Crete, enjoying his return to civilization, although he mentions some of the interesting friends they have made during this trip to South Africa, "the Boer farmers, Dutch station masters who gave us a corner under the telegraph table in which to sleep, with Nelson who kept the Transvaal Steam Laundry, Colonel Lynch of the steerage who comes to the dividing line to beg French books from Cecil" and interesting experiences in the Transvaal; they were unable to cable home before Naples, due to the presence of the plague at Aden, Suez, and Port Said; and shares how ill Cecil had been recently, 3 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:41)
- 1900 July 3 Telegram [from Richard and Cecil Davis] to L. Clark Davis, Napoli, message reads "Both well" (Box-folder 1:42)
- [1900] July 6 Richard [Harding Davis] to "Dear Family," Aix [Aix-en-Provence?], rejoiced at arriving after being on board ship for a month; everyone was so welcoming and kind; and Richard mentions his need to buy appropriate clothing for Europe, 2 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:43)
- [1900] July 7 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], both are settling in and getting rest and exercise; so far July is the coldest month they have had on their trip; will spend about a week in Paris; and is looking forward to home and real ragtime music, 2 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:44)
- 1900 July 10 Telegram from C. Anderson to L. Clark Davis, message reads "sailing St. Louis fourteenth home - sick to see you all at Marion - both well." (Box-folder 1:45)